<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Turtletopia: a blog about programming in R</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Turtletopia: a blog about programming in R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Overview: Sorting Version Codes</title>
      <link>/2022/07/16/overview-sort-version-codes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/07/16/overview-sort-version-codes/</guid>
      <description>Problem statement Solutions  Using base R Using gtools Using naturalsort Using stringr/stringi Using versionsort  Semantic version codes  Using semver Using semverutils  Conclusion   Problem statement Different versions of software are traditionally described using version codes. These codes contain usually numerical values and subsequent versions increment these codes, allowing them to be sorted. The standard is to use “semantic versioning”, where codes are in the form of “major.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating Observers in Loop. Shiny Reactivity Tricks: Episode 1</title>
      <link>/2022/07/09/creating-observers-in-loop-shiny-reactivity-tricks-episode-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/07/09/creating-observers-in-loop-shiny-reactivity-tricks-episode-one/</guid>
      <description>Preface Use case and naive solution A quick recap of environments Environments in Shiny Solution 1: Create an environment for each observer Solution 2: Inject the constants Solution 3 (or solution suggestion): Utilize Shiny modules Summary   Preface I’ve been recently working a lot in Shiny, and I’ve constantly been stumbling across new problems. Many of them seemed interesting enough for me to want to write an article.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello world</title>
      <link>/2022/07/01/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/07/01/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>Hi all!
I think it would be some aberration to start a programming blog with a post with any other title than &amp;ldquo;Hello world&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;
I am Dominik. I am a software developer and Data Science student (with the time of graduation approaching with high velocity). My friend Laura and I are passionate about programming in R. We love creating tools and playing with language to please others and ourselves (in any order).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
